Guide to the Eugene Clinton Haderlie Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Eugene Clinton Haderlie papers
1949-1994
SC0732
Haderlie, Eugene Clinton.
7 Linear feet
Collection includes research notes and notebooks (some during his graduate student years), 1949-94; class lectures, syllabi, and related materials, primarily from his Hopkins Marine Station classes, 1962-94; a few correspondence files, 1969-93; and correspondence, memoranda, minutes, financial records, and other items pertaining to the Monterey Bay Aquarium, 1978-89.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Haderlie earned his degrees in zoology at the University of California, Berkeley: A.B. 1943, M.A., 1948, and Ph.D., 1950. He has taught at the Monterey Peninsula College, University of California, Berkeley, Bodega Marine Laboratory, Naval Postgraduate School, and Hopkins Marine Station. Dr. Haderlie was National Science Foundation Fellow in 1958-59 and did research in England and Italy. He served as one of the senior scientists on the 1965 Te Vega expedition of Stanford University. His research interests are in the taxonomy of helminth parasites of fishes, marine invertebrate ecology, and marine boring and fouling organisms. He is one of the co-authors of the book INTERTIDAL INVERTEBRATES OF CALIFORNIA.
Description of the Collection
Collection includes research notes and notebooks (some during his graduate student years), 1949-94; class lectures, syllabi, and related materials, primarily from his Hopkins Marine Station classes, 1962-94; a few correspondence files, 1969-93; and correspondence, memoranda, minutes, financial records, and other items pertaining to the Monterey Bay Aquarium, 1978-89.
Access Terms
Haderlie, Eugene Clinton.; Hopkins Marine Station--Faculty.; Monterey Bay Aquarium.; Marine invertebrates.; Oceanography--Study and teaching.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Biographical Resume (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters from Students, 1983-93 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1969-85 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Answered Letters (1 of 2), 1982-85 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Answered Letters (2 of 2), 1983-84 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - U.C. Berkeley Reunion – 1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - U.C. Berkeley Research Notebook #1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - U.C. Berkeley Research Notebook #2 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - U.C. Berkeley Research Notebook #3, March 1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - U.C. Berkeley Research Notebook #4 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - U.C. Berkeley Research Notebook #5, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - U.C. Berkeley Research Notebook #6 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - U.C. Berkeley Research Notebook #7 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - U.C. Berkeley Research Notebook #8, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - University of Bristol Research Notebook, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Naval Postgraduate School Ecology Studies Notebook – 1971 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Deep Panel Fouling & Boring Study – June 1973 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Wharf Piling Studies – 1974 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Naval Postgraduate School Field Notes – 1978 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Field Notes Binder – 1994 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Stanford University: Hopkins Marine Station, Summer 1962 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Biology 101H Hopkins M.S. – 1964 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Biology 113H Hopkins M.S. – Summer 1975 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Biology 113H Hopkins M.S. – Summer 1976 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Biology 113H Hopkins M.S. – Summer 1977 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Biology 113H Hopkins M.S. – Summer 1978 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Biology 113H Hopkins M.S. – Summer 1979 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Biology 113H Hopkins M.S. – Summer 1980 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Biology 113H Hopkins M.S. – Summer 1981 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Biology 113H Hopkins M.S. – Summer 1982 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Biology 113H Hopkins M.S. – Summer 1983 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Biology 113H Hopkins M.S. – Summer 1985 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Biology 113H Hopkins M.S. – Summer 1986 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Biology 113H Hopkins M.S. – Summer 1987 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Biology 113H Hopkins M.S. – Summer 1988 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Biology 113H Hopkins M.S. – Summer 1989 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Biology 113H Hopkins M.S. – Summer 1990 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Biology 113H Hopkins M.S. – Summer 1991 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Biology 113H Hopkins M.S. – Summer 1992 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Biology 113H Hopkins M.S. – Summer 1993 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Biology 113H Hopkins M.S. – Summer 1994 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Biology 50: Biology & the Oceans – Winter 1986 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Oceanography 420 Lecture #1: General Biological Principles – 1978 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture #2: General Biological Principles II (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture #3: Origin & History of Life (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture #4: The Sea as a Biological Environment (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture #5: Taxonomy: Marine Plants (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture #6: Invertebrates I (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture #6: Invertebrates II (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture #7: Invertebrates III (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture #8: Invertebrates III (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture #9: Invertebrates IV (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture #10: Invertebrates V (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture #11: Plankton I (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture #12: Plankton II (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture #14: Marine Ecology; Food Cycles (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture #15: Nekton; Marine Vertebrates (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture #16: Vertebrates II; Fishes (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture #16B:Sea Birds (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Oc. 3420 Lecture #2: Osmoregulation (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Oc. 3420 Lecture #2A: Cellular Physiology (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Oc. 3420 Lecture #2B: Cellular Physiology (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Oc. 3420 Lecture #6: Marine Invertebrate Animals (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Oc 3420 Lecture #7: Marine Invertebrate Animals (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Oc. 3420 Lecture #10: Marine Invertebrate Animals (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Oc. 3420 Lecture #18: Vertebrates, Mammals IV (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture Materials: Post-Cambrian History of Life (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture Materials: Origin of Life (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture Materials: Chemical and Biological Evolution (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture Materials: Sexual and Asexual Reproduction (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture Materials: Mitosis Vs. Meiosis (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture Materials: Animal Cell Metabolism Reactions I (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture Materials: Animal Cell Metabolism Reactions II (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture Materials: Paralytic Shellfish Poisoning (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture Materials: Cellular Physiology (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture Materials: Boring Organisms; Marine Fouling (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture Materials: Embryology (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture Materials: Laboratory Assignment (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture Materials: Osmoregulation I, Fish Circulation (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture Materials: Osmoregulation II (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture Materials: Life of the Tide Zones (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture Materials: Reptiles and Sea Birds (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture Materials: Vertebrates III (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture Materials: Productivity (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture Materials: Farming the Sea (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture Materials: Echinodermata (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture Materials: Food Cycles in the Sea (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture Materials: Molting in Arthropods (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture Materials: Age of Microorganisms and Cell Structure (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Oc. 420 Lecture Materials: Bioluminescence (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - M.A.H. Chapter 1-2 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - M.A.H. Chapter 3: Cnidaria (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - M.A.H. Chapter 4-5 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - M.A.H. Chapter 6-7: Bryozoa, Brachiopods (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - M.A.H. Chapter 8-9: Asteroids and Hobtharoids (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - M.A.H. Chapter 10-11: Ophiuroids, Echinoids (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - M.A.H. Chapter 13: Prosobranchs (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - M.A.H. Chapter 14: Opithsobranchs (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - M.A.H. Chapter 15: Bivalves (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - M.A.H. Chapter 16-17: Chiton & Cephalopods (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - M.A.H. Chapter 19 Sipuncula Echiura (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - M.A.H. Chapter 20: Cirripedia (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - M.A.H. Chapter 21-22: Isopods, Tanaids, Amphiods (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - M.A.H. Chapter 23-28: Shrimps, Crustaceans, & Insects (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Rocky Creek Ecological Survey: Transect Data Sheets (1971-1973) (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Rocky Creek Ecological Survey: Map and Transect Slides (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Rocky Creek Ecological Survey: Photographs (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Report and Plates On New Species of Triganedistomum (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Acanthocephala Notes (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Allocreadiidae Notes (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Asteroidea Notes (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Brachiopoda, Phoronida Notes (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Bryozoa Notes (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Caryophyllaeidae Notes (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - The Chordate Egg and Early Development Notes (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Clinostomatidae Notes (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Cucullanidae Notes (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Dracunculidae Notes (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Diphullobothriidae Notes (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Echinodermata, Asteroidea Notes (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Copepods Notes (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Echinoidea Notes (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Echinoderms Notes (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Echinorhynchus Notes (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Fossils Notes (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Gorgoderidae Notes (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Gyrodactylidae Notes (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Heterocheiidae Notes (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Holothuroidea Notes (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Leeches Notes (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Lissorchiidae Notes (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Literature Survey Notes (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Neoechinorhynehus Notes (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - “The Oceanography of Monterey Bay” Notes (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Ophiuroidea Notes (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - “Overall Classification of Stomia and Ancestors of E-C Complex” Notes (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Paramphistomatidae Notes (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Pyllobothriidae Notes (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Plagiorchiidae Notes (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Proteocephalidae Notes (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Pteychobthriidae Notes (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Spiruridae Notes (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Strigeidae Notes (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - “Unidentified” Notes (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Master Copy – “Nemertea” (1978) (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Master Copy – “Platyhelminthes” (1978) (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Master Copy – “Coleuterata” (1978) (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - Master Copy – “Porifera” (1978) (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - Master Copy – “Foraminfera” (1978) (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - Master Copy – Preface and Introduction (1978) (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - “Intertidal Invertebrates of California” (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Corrections to “Intertidal Invertebrates of California” (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - SRI International: “Feasibility Analysis for Proposed Monterey Aquarium” (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - “An Introduction to the Monterey Bay Aquarium”(1978) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium – Back-up Data and References for PBQ&D, Inc. (1978) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - “An Introduction to the Monterey Bay Aquarium” (1979) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium – Blueprints (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium – Paul E. Davis Associates Architectural Report (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium – Newspaper Clippings (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium – “Education Objectives for One Year” (1983-1984) (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium – Exhibit Proposals (1984) (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Monterey Bay Research Committee Correspondence – 1983-1985 (1 of 3) (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Monterey Bay Research Committee Correspondence – 1983-1985 (2 of 3) (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Monterey Bay Research Committee Correspondence – 1983-1985 (3 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Aquarium Guide Training Course (1984) (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium – Abridged Guide Handbook (1984) (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium –Guide Manual (1984) (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium Research Advisory Committee – 1986 (1 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium Research Advisory Committee – 1986 (2 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium Research Advisory Committee – 1987 (1 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium Research Advisory Committee – 1987 (2 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium – Tours and Travel Committee (1989) (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - M.B.A. Teachers’ Institute Papers (1990) (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium Financial Statements (1985) (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium Financial Statements (1985-1986) (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium – 1986 Goals and Proposals (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium Board of Trustees – Correspondence (1986) (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium Foundation Financial Statements (1986-1987) (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium – Annual Budget (1987) (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium Board of Trustees –Meeting Minutes and Correspondence (1987) (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - “An Analysis and Plan for a Community Relations Program for the Monterey Bay Aquarium” (1987 May) (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Articles of Incorporation, Bylaws and Minutes of the First Meeting of Monterey Bay Aquarium Board of Trustees (1978) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium Board of Trustees – Minutes from Meetings (1980-1983) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium Board of Trustees – June 1, 1984, Meeting Minutes (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium Board of Trustees – Miscellaneous Notes (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium Board of Trustees – Education Department Memos (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium Board of Trustees –Meeting Minutes and Correspondence (1988) (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium Board of Trustees – Financial Statements and Budget (1990-1991) (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium Board of Trustees – Memos and Budgetary Information (1990-1991) (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium Board of Trustees – Proposals and Projects (1989-1991) (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium Board of Trustees – Comprehensive Package (1990) (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium Board of Trustees – 1989 Budget Package (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium – Sea Otter Research Program (1988) (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium – Goals and Proposed Projects (1988) (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium Board of Trustees – Budget Proposals (1984-1986) (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium Board of Trustees – Memorandums (1984-1986) (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium Board of Trustees – Meeting Notes (1984-1986) (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium Economic Impact Review (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium Board of Trustees – Year End Report (1988) (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Monterey Bay Aquarium Board of Trustees – Proposed Budget (1989) (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Oversize Lecture Slides (overhead variety) (Box 5)